Finding aid to the Dorothy Stahl papers CA.MS.00145
Smith College Archives
Dorothy Stahl papers
1915-2003
1925-1999
Smith College Archives
Stahl, Dorothy
CA.MS.00145
1.25 linear feet (14 containers)
Dorothy Stahl was a Professor of Music and singer. The collection contains diaries, correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, and sound recordings.
Biographical / Historical
Dorothy Stahl was born December 3, 1918 in Toledo, OH the only child of George Peter and Lola (Torbet) Stahl. She began taking piano lessons at the age of six but did not begin pursuing singing until the age of 16. Dorothy was educated in the public schools in Toledo and graduated from De Vilbiss High School in 1936. She began her undergraduate education at Toledo University where she concentrated on courses in Music and French. She transferred to the Chicago Musical College in the fall of 1939 and studied with voice teacher Graham Reed. Her skills progressed rapidly and she was awarded the Oliver Ditson Scholarship for $1,000.
After graduating with a Bachelor of Music degree in 1942, she went directly to the Juilliard Graduate School in New York with a four-year fellowship. She studied voice with Queena Mario, a former opera singer with the Metropolitan Opera. The war prevented Dorothy from studying in Europe and Juilliard compensated by providing the voice students stage experience in a series of productions. She sang leading roles in Der Freishutz Cosi fan tutte, The Secret Marriage by Cimarosa, and Puccini's La Rondine. She received her certificate from Juilliard in 1946.
During her early career she sang leading roles with the Chautauqua Opera Company, was a soloist with the Desoff Choir and the National Symphony Orchestra, and appeared on the Columbia Broadcasting Company as soloist on the "Church of the Air" and "New Voices in Song" programs. She aspired to being a member of the Metropolitan Opera and was a finalist in the Metropolitan Opera Audition of the Air in 1948. Two years later she gave her first Town Hall Recital in New York City.
Dorothy began her teaching career in 1952 at Centenary Junior College in Hackettstown, NJ. She was soon persuaded to join the faculty at Smith College where she began teaching voice students in September of 1955. Dorothy was highly involved in the life of the college and her department. She served on Music Department committees, appeared in every faculty show, gave numerous recitals, served as College Marshal, and was dedicated to her voice students. She published A Selected Discography of Solo Song in 1968 and followed that with five editions the last of which was published in 1984 the year she retired. Dorothy battled Parkinson's Disease for many years and died on April 3, 2003.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains diaries, correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, newspaper clippings and sound recordings. The collection provides a comprehensive overview of the career and personal life of Dorothy Stahl. The scrapbooks and newspaper clippings give information about her performances and the sound recordings are excellent examples of her singing abilities. She keeps a diary starting in 1931 and they are short entries but somewhat introspective. As Dorothy gets older her diary entries divulge less about her inner thoughts and more about her daily activities and the state of the weather. The diaries also show her failing health visually through the detrioration of the handwriting as the Parkinson's disease makes it more difficult for her to write.
Related Material
See also:
42.Silbert, Doris - retirement party music
42. Putman, Raymond - retirement party music
100. Audio-Visual Collection
52. Music Department records
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Carol Gotwals, executor of the estate of Dorothy Stahl, donated this collection to the College Archives, in July 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
- Academic records, 1925-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Baby Book, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Biographical information, 1918-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Centenary Junior College, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Chatauqua Institution, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Chicago Musical College, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Clippings - newspaper, 1934-1967; undated (Box 1, Folder 6a)
- Concert programs, 1928-1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Concert programs, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Concert programs, 1950-1982; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Concert - Town Hall, New York, 11 Mar 1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1933-1988; undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Boepple, Paul, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Friends from International House in New York, 1945-1972; undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jacobi, Frederick, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Mario, Queena, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Reed, Graham, 1941-1951 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Smith College - appointments, salary, promotions, 1955-1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Stahl, Lola and George, 1939-1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Students, 1957-1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Written by Dorothy Stahl, 1926; 1934; 1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Courses - Diction, 1978; undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Family, 1917-1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- High School Yearbook - Thomas A. De Vilbiss High School, Toledo, OH, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- International House, New York City, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Juilliard School of Music, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Metropolitan Opera Audition of the Air, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Miscellaneous, 1931-1949; undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Mu Phi Epsilon Sorority, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- National Music League Quartet, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Passports, 1962; 1980; 1985 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Photographs
  - Career, 1943-1966; undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Childhood, 1918-1936 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Family, 1920-1960; undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Family - Lola (Torbet) Stahl and George Peter Stahl, 1915-1960s (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Friends, 1930s-1999 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Portraits, 1921-1970 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Teaching and students, 1956-1964; undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Travel, 1950; 1964; undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Voice teachers - Queena Mario and Graham Reed, 1941-1951 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Publication - Research material for Discography, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Publication - A Selective Discography of Solo Song correspondence, contracts, reviews, 1968-1984 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Retirement - concert and party correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Scrapbook, 1928-1939 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Scrapbook - correspondence, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Smith College course work, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Diaries, 1931-1934; 1939; 1941; 1942; 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Diaries, 1953-1962 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Diaries, 1963-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Diaries, 1973-1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Diaries, 1983-1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Diaries, 1993-1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Diaries - Travel, 1953-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Sound Recordings - arranged chronologically
  - Metropolitan Opera broadcasts: Singing a duet from Hansel and Gretel, Queena Mario - soprano, Irene Jessner - soprano?; Singing an unidentified duet in English, Queena Mario - soprano, Mario Martinnelli - tenor, 1930s (Box 12.TR, 42.Stahl Mario, Queena)
  - Metropolitan Opera Audition of the Air, Dorothy Stahl's audition pieces: Madga's Waltz from "La Rondine" by Puccini Vilia from "The Merry Widow" by Franz Lehar; Bess, You Is My Woman Now from "Porgy and Bess" by Gershwin, Duet with Frank Guarrera - baritone; Depuis le Jour from "Louise" by Gustav Charpentier; Duet of the Flowers from "Madame Butterfly" by Puccini, Duet with Jane Hobson - mezzo soprano; Legere hirondelles from "Mignon" by Ambrose Thomas, Duet with unidentified male bass singer; Pourquoi arrachez vous a ma sombre demeure from "La Juive" by Fromental Halevy, Duet with Gertrude Ribla - dramatic soprano, 1948 (Box 12.TR, 42.Stahl, Met auditions)
  - Metropolitan Opera Audition of the Air, Dorothy Stahl's audition pieces, 1948 (Box CD52)
  - Town Hall Recital - New York City: Dorothy Stahl - soprano, Robert Payson Hill - piano, 11 Mar 1950 (Box 12.TR, 42.Stahl, Town Hall)
  - Town Hall Recital - New York City: Dorothy Stahl - soprano, Robert Payson Hill - piano, 11 Mar 1950 (Box CD53)
  - Christmas Vespers: Regina Coeli by Mozart; Smith College Choir; Harvard Glee Club; Dorothy Stahl - soprano soloist, Dec 1956 (Box 12.TR, 80.SD Christmas 1956)
  - WNYC Festival of American Music (radio show): 3 poems set to music by John Duke; Shelley - "My Soul is an Enchanted Boat"; James Stevens - "A Bird Sings Now"; e.e. cummings - "the mountains are dancing", Doris Silbert - narrator, Dorothy Stahl - soprano. John Duke - piano, 17 Feb 1957 (Box 12.TR, 42.Stahl)
  - Thomas Mendenhall's Inauguration: 3 Sonnets by Edna St. Vincent Millay set to music by John Duke; "Sweet sounds, oh, beautiful music, do not cease"; "Time does not bring relief; you all have lied"; "Thou famished grave, I will not fill the yet", Dorothy Stahl - soprano, Louise Rood - viola, John Duke - piano, Oct 1959 (Box 12.TR, 42.Stahl, Millay sonnets)
  - Smith College Museum of Art - Recital for the exhibition "Henri Fantin-Latour": Dorothy Stahl - soprano, Lory Wallfisch - piano, Ernst Wallfisch - viola, 18 May 1966 (Box 12.TR, 42.Stahl, Museum of Art)
  - Recital: Dorothy Stahl - soprano, Robert Miller - piano, 9 Oct 1966 (Box 12.TR, 42.Stahl, Recital 1966)
  - Faculty Recital: Dorothy Stahl - soprano, Robert Miller - piano, Philipp Naegele - violin, John Sessions - celo, William Wittig - flute, 2 Feb 1969 (Box 12.TR, 42.Stahl,Recital 1969 #1 and #2)
  - Recital #2: Dorothy Stahl - soprano, Unidentified pianist, undated (Box 12.TR, 42.Stahl, Recital)